<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of meekenesse preached at the Spittle vpon Easter Tuesday, M.D.C.XXIII. By William Rawley, Doctor of Diuinity.</title>
            <author>Rawley, William, 1588?-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 934:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of meekenesse preached at the Spittle vpon Easter Tuesday, M.D.C.XXIII. By William Rawley, Doctor of Diuinity.</title>
                  <author>Rawley, William, 1588?-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for Matthew Lownes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF Meekeneſſe, PREACHED AT THE SPITTLE vpon EASTER <hi>Tueſday,</hi> M.D.C.XXIII.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Rawley,</hi> Doctor of Diuinity.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN HAVILAND for <hi>Matthew Lownes,</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5460:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5460:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FRANCIS Lord VERVLAN, <hi>Viſcount</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. ALBAN, my truely Noble LORD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is more reaſon for the Dedication of this Sermon to your Lordſhip, then for the Impreſsion of it. Your Acceptance of me to be yours, before you had any other of my Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: The timely fruit of your fauour, in my Aduancement vnto that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, by which J ſubſiſt: My At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance vpon your Employments, and Seruices, at this preſent: And whatſoeuer is any way eminent either in my Eſtate, or Name, J am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to aſcribe it to your Lordſhip, from
<pb facs="tcp:5460:3"/>whence J haue receiued it. For the printing of this Booke, I can ſay lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. Jt is not any greedy Appetite of Life, wherein it can take comfort, but rather the contrary, wherewith euery thing is naturally touched, Feare of Death and Obliuion. And yet if it be proper to any Diſcourſes, thoſe of this nature are fitteſt to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue the first Birth, becauſe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine <hi>the vncorruptible ſeed which dieth not.</hi> Beſides, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sermons haue this priuiledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Vocall Sermons onely, that they may be <hi>inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon.</hi> J pray God to proſper your Lordſhips Perſon, and Affaires.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and truly deuoted Seruant, W. RAVVLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5460:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 5.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Bleſſed are the Meeke, for they ſhall inherit the Earth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text carries vs vp to the Mount of Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Holineſſe, and Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and is one of the eight ſteps, by which wee may climbe vnto heauenly Beatitude. Our Sauiour Chriſt, when he vnfolded theſe Myſteries vnto the world, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp into the Mountaine; A place choſen to reſemble the height of thoſe things, hee intended to deliuer. The Company, that was preſent, were onely his Diſciples, perſons of more iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5460:4"/>and penetration, then the common Multitude. And though it be certaine, that our Sauiours wiſdome, might vſe theſe circumſtances, for other cauſes, yet they are not vnfit Arguments to put a diſtinction, betwixt other his ordinary Sayings, and theſe myſterious Sentences. And yet if we deſcend, to the opinion of the world, there is nothing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth vs ſo low, as the practiſe of theſe eight Beatitudes; <hi>Pouerty in Spirit, Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Meekeneſſe,</hi> and the reſt; ſubiects of vulgar ſcorne, and vnſupportable miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: but ſuch is the gratiouſneſſe of God, that he hath promiſed by his Prophets,
<hi>to raiſe vp the poore out of the duſt;</hi> and <hi>to wipe away all teares from the eies of the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> and laſtly, <hi>that he will beautifie the meeke with ſaluation;</hi> and he alſo performeth it. I haue thought fit, to preſent before this great Aſſembly, at this time, one of theſe eight Beatitudes, in particular that of Meekeneſſe: Firſt, becauſe it was the emploiment of the beſt Preacher, when he liued vpon the earth: <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is vpon me, becauſe the Lord hath annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5460:4"/>me, to preach good tidings vnto the Meeke, Iſai.</hi> 61. It was ſpoken in prophecy of our Sauiour Chriſt, and is now the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of euery Chriſtian Miniſter. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe I know no ſubiect more vſefull, in the common calamities, and troubles of this world, than Meekeneſſe is; in which wee haue ſuch continuall need, to apply that ſalue of our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Phyſitian, <hi>In your patience poſſeſſe yee your ſoules, Luc.</hi>
21. And laſtly, becauſe it is not altogether impertinent vnto this Time, in which the Meekeneſſe of our Sauiour hath exalted him to a ioyfull and glorious Reſurrection, according as it is acknowledged by Saint <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 2. <hi>Hee humbled himſelfe vnto death</hi> — <hi>Wherefore</hi> (that implies the cauſe) <hi>God alſo hath highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted him, and giuen him a name which is aboue euery name.</hi> And although, it may ſeeme a ſubiect, vnfit for a mixt Aſſembly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that our Sauiours wiſdome, ſingled out his Diſciples, when he firſt proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this Beatitude; <hi>Bleſſed are the meeke:</hi> Yet I am ſure, that exhortation of Chriſt was generall, and recommended to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5460:5"/>the whole multitude, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>Learne of me, for I am meeke, and lowly of heart.</hi> Now being to proceed in this Treatiſe of Meekeneſſe, I cannot begin better, then to craue a taſte of it, in your preſent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, in thoſe words, wherewith
<hi>S. Cypr.</hi> beginneth his booke <hi>de bono patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae. De patientiâ locuturus, vnde potiùs incipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, quam quod nunc quoque ad audientiam, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram patientiam video eſſenceſſariam:</hi> Or to change it into the ſtile and authority of Saint <hi>Iames, Receiue with meekeneſſe, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted word, which is able to ſaue your ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The particulars, which I ſhall handle, in the vnfolding of this Text, may be all reduced to theſe three maine Heads. The firſt is, the Condition, or Eſtate of men, whom our Sauiour Chriſt, amongſt ſome others, repeated both before, and after my Text, is pleaſed to glorifie. <hi>The Meeke.</hi> In which part, it will not be vnſeaſonable, to lay downe a Modell, of the Vertue of Meekeneſſe, and to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, both in the Properties, and Kinds, the Oppoſites, the Preſeruatiues, and ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5460:5"/>like, with the circumſtances belonging vnto it. The ſecond is, the Dignity and Sublimity of ſuch perſons, as are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in this Vertue of Meekneſſe;
<hi>Bleſſed:</hi> ſhewing that it is not only a Vertue, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Morall or Theologicall, but which is more, a Beatitude or Bleſſedneſſe. The third is the Reward, which is promiſed, to the practiſers of this Vertue, whether it be of temporall Bleſſings, or of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Bleſſings, or of both; <hi>For they ſhall inherit the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin with the firſt. The Condition, or Eſtate of men, who are here pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Bleſſed, are the Meeke. And firſt, that it may be plaine, who the Meeke perſons be, we ſhall finde this Vertue to be deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, by the Morall Philoſophers, and Schoole-Diuines both, that it is <hi>Moderatiua irarum; A moderation about the paſsion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> The Schoole-men haue a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not vnprofitable, concerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall offices of the Morall Vertues; namely, that ſome Vertues are exerciſed about the Actions of men, others about the Paſſions. Thoſe that are exerciſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5460:6"/>about the Actions, are the moſt eaſie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nothing elſe to doe, but to obſerue an euen, and golden Mediocrity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two Extremes. As Liberality is to obſerue a meane, in the Action of giuing, which may encline, neither vnto Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, nor Prodigality. Thoſe that are exerciſed about the Paſſions, are more difficult, hauing a double emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in that there is a golden Medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity to be obſerued, and an inordinate Affection to be ſubdued. This Vertue of Meekeneſſe, is about a Paſſion. Beſides, amongſt the Paſſions, ſome are more tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, and gentle, others altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable. That of Anger, is the moſt furious, and vnreſiſtable Paſſion, of the whole number. In regard whereof, the temper of Meekeneſſe, in perſons capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it, is the more rare, and excellent; firſt that it is not a Mediocrity onely, but a Moderation: Secondly a Moderation, not of any ordinary, or relenting Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but of the ſuddeneſt, and moſt vnruly Paſſion of all, that is anger. The Extreme on the one ſide, that is in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5460:6"/>the Exceſſe, is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Indignation,</hi> or
<hi>Wrath:</hi> and the other Extreme, in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, vnto which Meekeneſſe moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth (though that alſo muſt be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed as a Vice) is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>Lenitude,</hi> or an <hi>Incapabilitie of Anger.</hi> The words, which doe ſignifie a Meeke perſon, both in the Latine and Greeke, doe ſet forth two Properties, which are found in him. Firſt, becauſe Anger is a Commotion, and Vnquietneſſe in our owne Breaſts, ſuch a moderate perſon, is in Latine called <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> and that word is well expreſſed by
<hi>Virgil,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mitis vt in morem ſtagni, placida<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> paludis:</hi> Reſembling the Meeke man, to a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding water, where neither the Streame, nor the Tide doe tranſport it, nor the Winde much wrinckle the face of it. Againe, becauſe Anger is an outward Harſhneſſe, or Way wardneſſe towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the Greeke name frees him from that, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, deriued as it may ſeeme from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is eaſie, declaring a Facility, and Gentleneſſe, in the outward Comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Behauiour.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5460:7"/>
            <p>Next heereunto are the kindes of Meekeneſſe, which we ſhall finde to be double; Toward God, and toward Man. Anſwerable to the two ſorts of Anger. For there is One, that caſteth a Stone vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which is cenſured by <hi>Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus;</hi> and there is Another, that ſhooteth his Arrowes forward, as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> did, though he were warranted by
<hi>Eliſha.</hi> And <hi>Hee that caſteth a ſtone on high,</hi> aimeth it againſt God,
<hi>and it ſhall fall vpon his owne head, Eccleſ.</hi> 27. and He that ſhooteth his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes forward, leuelleth them againſt Man, intending the Deſtruction of his Enemies. Now though the two kindes of Meekeneſſe aboue named, may bee both one Action, and he that is Meeke towards God, will be Meeke alſo towards Man, and ſo on the contrary, from Man to God; yet becauſe the Obiect is ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and requires a double Qualification in our Mindes, I may be licenſed to diuide it into theſe two ſtreames, and to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle them ſeuerally, in my Diſcourſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. The former is a franke, and conſtant ſubmiſſion of our deſires, in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5460:7"/>all things, vnto the mighty pleaſure of God. And the other, an amiable, and vſefull Conuerſation towards all Men. The Oppoſite, vnto the former, is a Repining, and Murmuring againſt God; and vnto the ſecond, either a Prouocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Brother by Wrong, or a Thirſt of Reuenge, whether the Iniury be true, or pretended. We will begin with the former, A Submiſſion, vnder the mighty Hand of God. This Vertue is recorded, in the 37. Pſalme, <hi>But thoſe that wait vpon the Lord, they ſhall inherit the earth.</hi> From this Pſalme, is the Beatitude transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> in expreſſe words: The Argument of the Pſalme, is wholly vpon that ſtring, <hi>Patient waiting vpon the Lord:</hi> The Reward is the ſame, <hi>They ſhall inherit the Earth:</hi> All theſe ſhew it to be a ſpeciall branch, of this Vertue of Meekeneſſe.</p>
            <p>There are two ordinary Motiues, of our Indignation, and Murmuring againſt God. The one is, the proſperous Eſtate of the vngodly: the other, the vnproſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Eſtate (as we deeme it) of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5460:8"/>Concerning the former. Wee ſhall finde nothing, that did ſo much fill with wonder, euen the beſt ſort of Men, as theſe waies of God, in proſpering of the wicked.
<hi>Aſaph</hi> was a Prophet, and one of the ſweet Singers, and yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into this Contemplation, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>that his feet were almoſt gone, and his ſteps had well nigh ſlipt, Pſal.</hi> 73. <hi>Iob</hi> was a Patterne of Patience; and yet he thought he did wiſely, in recounting the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Wicked, to the ſilencing of his Friends,
<hi>Iob</hi> 21. <hi>Ieremy</hi> the Prophet, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with God, vpon the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<hi>Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper, Ier.</hi> 12? But theſe Men, though they were at the firſt ſtumbled, went forward into <hi>the Sanctuary of God,</hi> and with Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe reſted, vpon his righteous Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments towards the vngodly. The Vice therefore, which doth moſt oppoſe Meekeneſſe, is <hi>Aemulatio propter impios,</hi> which is the Stile of the 37. Pſalme, <hi>Fret not thy ſelfe, becauſe of the vngodly.</hi> The Sentence, denounced againſt the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that Pſalme, is alwaies iuſt, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5460:8"/>
               <hi>For they ſhall ſoone be cut downe, as the graſſe, and wither as the greene herb.</hi> The Flower of the Vngodly, heere in this World, howſoeuer it may ſeeme to grow vp ſpecious, and goodly, yet is it alwaies ſhort, and momentany, the Righteouſneſſe of God, and the Fulneſſe of their Iniquity, pulling downe in the end, due Vengeance, and Wrath vpon them. <hi>At vſque quo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> is our complaint, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. <hi>Lord how long ſhall the wicked, how long ſhall the wicked Triumph?</hi> The time is not long:
<hi>Quoniàm adhùc modicùm,</hi> as in the firſt of <hi>Hoſea, Yet a little while, and I will auenge the bloud of Iez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reel.</hi> Nay the finall Condemnation of them is at hand, <hi>For Behold I come quickly, and my reward is with me, Apoc.</hi> 22. It is the Saying of
<hi>S. Auguſt. Infirmitas facit diù vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, quòd citò eſt.</hi> Our Deſires, are like the Deſires of ſicke Perſons, vnto whom that ſeemes long which is not ſo indeed, but becauſe we meaſure the time, by our diſtempered Appetites, and Infirmity. If we ſhould meaſure our Deſires, by a temporall rule only, it is not manners
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5460:9"/>for vs, to preſſe for Reuenge, whileſt our Betters are vnreuenged. <hi>The ſoules from vnder the altar</hi> (namely thoſe of the deare Martyrs of God) are not yet auenged, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 6. It is the caſe of God himſelfe, who if he were ſo iealous, and angry a God, he would not ſuffer an Altar to ſmoake, nor an Idoll to be adored, nor an hypocriticall Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be offered, nor a blaſphemous Oath to be vttered, without inſtantly conſuming the Offendors: At leaſt, he would not diuide ſo patiently, his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall fauours, of the Sunne, and Raine, amongſt the Iuſt, and Vniuſt, without diſtinction. To proceed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Nec dum vindicatus eſt, ipſe qui vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat,</hi> as <hi>S. Coprian</hi> ſaith; The Sonne of God himſelfe, is not yet auenged, for all thoſe foule Reproaches, and Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities done vnto him. And though <hi>the Father hath committed all iudgement to the ſonne, Iohn</hi> 5. and ſo he hath the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his owne hands; nay, and (which is more) he hath inueſted himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Iudicature: <hi>Vengeance belongeth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5460:9"/>vnto me, I will recompence, ſaith the Lord, Heb.</hi> 10. notwithſtanding he delayeth to execute deſerued wrath vpon his Enemies. And heerein appeareth, the wonderfull Sufferance, and Meekeneſſe, of our Sauiour Chriſt; <hi>Vt qui in coelis adoretur, nec dum vindicetur in terris,</hi> as the ſame Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaketh, That hee, whom the whole Hoaſt of Heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doreth, ſhould ſuffer an Hoaſt of Wormes, and Miſcreants, to blaſpheme him vpon the earth. Laſtly, it is no leſſe Curioſity, to ſearch into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God concerning the eſtate of the wicked, then Preſumption to ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite their ſubuerſion, before the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed day. What, and if it bee the will of God, <hi>that both ſhould grow vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> (the Wicked and the Iuſt) <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the harueſt, Matth.</hi>
13? <hi>What and if God willing to ſhew his wrath, and to make his power knowne, endureth with much long ſuffering, the veſſels of wrath, fitted to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, Rom.</hi> 9? And this is to appeaſe the firſt Motiue, of our Murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and Indignation againſt God,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5460:10"/>for the Proſperity of the wicked.</p>
            <p>The other Motiue, which armeth vs, with Indignation, and Murmuring againſt God, is the ſenſe of ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miſery, whether it be, in our Soule, or our Body, or our Goods, or any other way, wherein the hand of God layeth heauy vpon vs. This ſecond Motiue, toucheth vs more neerely, then the former, and is like vnto that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Deuill thought, to haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an ouerthrow, againſt <hi>Iobs</hi> Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; <hi>But put forth thine Hand now, and touch his bone, and his fleſh, and he will curſe thee to thy face.</hi> In this diſtreſſe, the Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame holy Man <hi>Iob,</hi> will be very proper to enter into our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations;
<hi>Shall we receiue good from God, and ſhall we not receiue euill alſo?</hi> The Fountaine of all our good, is God, and if he be pleaſed, to turne our ſweet, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a little bitterneſſe, why ſhould wee repine, againſt the Omnipotent wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our Maker? Againe, if we be Gods Children, the Afflictions that come from him, are not for our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5460:10"/>but for our Triall, and to make vs ſhine more gloriouſly: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will turne to our aduantage, when we ſhall come to reape the fruit of our ſuffrings, and that
<hi>Quantò in hoc ſeculo frangimur, tantò in futaro ſolidamur;</hi> as Saint
<hi>Bern<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſaith: The more we are ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in this world, the more we are roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and grounded in glory. Neither is it of ſmall force, to exaſperate, or mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie our Afflictions, the behauiour wee vſe in taking of them; ſeeing it is true, as Saint <hi>Cypr.</hi> ſaith,
<hi>In ſenſu doloris eſt omne quod punit: Griefe is according to the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of him that beares it.</hi> And therefore the ſame Author S. <hi>Cypr.</hi> had very good reaſon, to put a diffe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rence, betwixt the ſufferings of the Righteous, and of others, that repined with a Heatheniſh Impiety: In his Booke <hi>ad Demetrianum: Putatis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aduerſa Vobiſcum aequalitèr perpeti, cum eadem aduerſa videatis à Nobis, &amp; vobis, non aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licèr ſuſtineri.</hi> There may be the ſame Latitude of paines, inflicted vpon two ſeuerall Perſons, and yet the ſenſe, and Impreſſion of them much different,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5460:11"/>whilſt the one beares them, with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and calme minde, the other with a querulous, and vnquiet reluctation. But the beſt Argument is that of Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi>
8. <hi>For I reckon, that the ſuffrings of this preſent time, are not worthy to be compared with the glory, that ſhall be reuealed in vs.</hi> And if there be ſo much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, betwixt our preſent Enduring, and our future Glory, there is as great inequality, betwixt the Offence of our Murmuring againſt God, and the Cauſe of it, being for ſo ſmall matters, as the tranſitory Pelfe of this world, which are no better, then the fading delight of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> cenſured by God himſelfe, <hi>Doeſt thou well to be angry for the gourd? Looking vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ieſus, the Authour, and finiſher of our faith Heb.</hi> 12. The Scope, and Comfort, of euery Chriſtians profeſſion: And he that looketh vnto <hi>Ieſus,</hi> as he ought, cannot be much amated, at the euill Aſpects of worldly Happineſſe. Finally, who can tell, whether it be not, as Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Praecordia fatui, ſicut rota currûs, foenum portans, &amp; murmurans?</hi> For there
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5460:11"/>is Murmuring in Fulneſſe, as well as in Emptineſſe, like the Wheele of a Carre, that goeth on creaking, and yet carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away a full load. And we finde, that the greateſt Murmurers were the Children of Iſrael, People that had the moſt ſaturity, and were oft repleniſht with a Miracle. But they receiued the due reward of their Murmuring, being ſtung to death by Serpents. The Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murer hath the Poyſon of Serpents, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his tongue, wherewith he wounds God, and it is iuſt for him, to receiue his Deaths wound by the Poyſon of a Serpent. To conclude this part; The Root, from whence Chriſtian Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſprings, is
<hi>Humility;</hi> the foremoſt in the ranke of theſe eight Beatitudes; that is <hi>Pouerty in Spirit:</hi> And it was the Confeſſion of an humble Spirit, yet not of an abiect (eſpecially being vttered in the Figure of Chriſt) <hi>For I am a worme and no man, Pſalm.</hi> 22. Then what am I, that I ſhould turne againe, vpon my Maker? And this ſhall be ſufficient, to appeaſe our Murmuring, and Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5460:12"/>againſt God, cauſed from thoſe two Motiues: The proſperous Eſtate of the Vngodly, and the vnproſperous Eſtate of the Godly. And thus much for the firſt Kinde of our Meekeneſſe, toward God.</p>
            <p>The other Kinde of Meekeneſſe, is exerciſed in a gracious, and vſefull Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, toward all Men. And this Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is recommended vnto <hi>Timothy,</hi> by the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul:</hi> In whoſe ſpeech, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted ſome things, peculiar to a Biſhop, other things generall for all Men. <hi>And the ſeruant of the Lord muſt not ſtriue, but be gentle vnto all men, apt to teach, patient: In meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe inſtructing, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo forward. There are three euill Properties, reigning in the Breaſts of the greater part, that doe beare an euill Aſpect, to this Kinde of Meekeneſſe, toward Man. The firſt is <hi>Auger,</hi> that Quality that is called in Latine <hi>Iracundia;</hi> A Diſpoſition euer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be on fire, and is as well vnſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable to our ſelues, as to others. The ſecond is <hi>Harmefulneſſe,</hi> or a malignant Deſire of doing wrong, without any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5460:12"/>offence, or occaſion giuen. The third is a <hi>Thirst of Reuenge,</hi> after an Iniury concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, whether the Wrong be true, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. Theſe three muſt be calmed, and appeaſed, before we can prepare a roome, for the Vertue of Meekeneſſe.</p>
            <p>To begin with the firſt, that is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The Perſons, that are prone to this euill diſeaſe, are of the nature of a Burning Coale, or a Thorne full of Prickles, on euery ſide: I meane not for their deſire to hurt, or to conſume o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (for thoſe are the Properties of the following Kindes) but becauſe they are alwaies ſo Hot, or ſo Sharp, that you cannot touch them. And firſt this Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, (for I finde no better teſtimony of it) is the Quality of a Foole. <hi>Anger reſteth in the boſome of fooles,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> in the ſeuenth chapter; vnto which agreeth the Saying of Saint <hi>Bernard: Tantò qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincitur minùs ſapiens, quantò eſt minùs Patien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> A man is vndoubtedly conuinced, to want ſo much of the Power of Wiſdome, as he wants of the Vertue of Patience Againe, it is a Paſſion, that tranſport
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5460:13"/>vs immoderately, beyond the Bounds of Reaſon; the Glory, and Priuiledge of Mankinde. And I haue read it in one, that expreſſeth this Exceſſe not vntruly;
<hi>Cogitationes iracundi vipereae ſunt generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, mentem comedunt matrem ſuam.</hi> The thoughts of an irefull Man, are of the Vipers Brood, deuouring Reaſon the Mother that bare them. And though it be the Property of other Paſſions, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt Reaſon, <hi>for the fleſh luſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit;</hi> yet in them, <hi>the ſpirit,</hi> againe,
<hi>luſteth againſt the fleſh,</hi> and none of them doth ſo mightily ouerthrow, and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vpon Reaſon, as Anger doth. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, it is a Paſſion, that is apteſt to vex the Holy Spirit of God, which is giuen vs, for our ſanctification. <hi>S. Paul</hi> writeth in the fourth to the Epheſians, <hi>And grieue not the holy ſpirit of God, whereby ye are ſealed vnto the day of Redemption.</hi> To auoid this, he aduiſeth in the Verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; <hi>Let all bitterneſſe, and wrath, and Anger</hi> — <hi>be put away from you.</hi> In theſe and many other, conſiſteth the Deformity of this Vice; It ſetteth vpon a Man the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5460:13"/>Badge of folly, tranſporteth him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Bounds of Reaſon, grieueth the Holy Spirit of God which is giuen vnto him.</p>
            <p>The Second Property is <hi>Harmefulneſſe,</hi> or the firſt Prouocation by Wrong.
<hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> faith of Moroſity, or Peeuiſhneſſe, that it is <hi>Delicatum iracundiae genus,</hi> A dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty kinde of Anger: wherein he hitteth it right, for it is ſo nice, and queaſie, that nothing can wooe it to Patience. This Vice, vpon which we now inſiſt, may be ſometimes called <hi>Mortiferum iracundiae ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> A deadly kinde of Anger; for it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth Miſchiefe, and hurt to him, at whom it is aymed. And theſe Natures are more vngentle then <hi>Nabal;</hi> for <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> though he parted not with his goods, at the ſolicitation of <hi>Dauid,</hi> yet hee ſought to doe him no harme; but there was a Nature, noted by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> for a notorious euill condition; <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Copperſmith hath done me much euill.</hi> That which was ſpoken in Prophecy, of the Iewes wicked hatred againſt our Sauiour Chriſt, was in this ranke of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5460:14"/>Anger, <hi>They hated me without a cauſe:</hi> for he ſuſtained many Iniuries, and wrongs, which he neuer deſerued. This Kinde of Anger, can haue no better cenſure, then <hi>Homo homini Lupus,</hi> and I hope it is a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition more frequent amongſt wilde Beaſts, then Men. Laſtly, Our Sauiour Chriſt hath damned it, with a perpetuall blot; <hi>But woe to that man, by whom the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence commeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Property oppoſite to Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is a <hi>Thirſt of Reuenge,</hi> after an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury receiued. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith likewiſe, in this point of Reuenge, <hi>Inhumanum verbum vltio;</hi> Vindication, or Reuenge is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Word; the Action it ſelfe, is farre more inhumane. The Saying of the ſame Authour <hi>Seneca,</hi> is a good Tenet in Morality.
<hi>Non vt in benefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ijs, honeſtum eſt merita meritis repenſare, ita iniurias iniurijs; illic vinci turpe eſt, hic vincere.</hi> Iniuries are not of the nature of Benefits, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited with the like, as one Benefit with another; And the Contention in the one is laudable, but in the other, it is ſoule, and diſhonourable. This made the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5460:14"/>
               <hi>Cato,</hi> when hee was ſtricken at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, and the party came, to tender ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, for that Iniury, to put it off with ſo much lightneſſe: <hi>Non memini percuſſum me;</hi> I remember not, that I was ſtricken. And the ſame Spirit of Patience, and bearing Iniuries, liued in many of the Auncient Worthies, <hi>Alexander, the two firſt Caeſars,</hi> together with ſome Philoſophers, and others. And the Principle, that they held, for the bearing of Iniuries, was Magnanimity, according as <hi>Seneca,</hi> one of the lateſt of them hath expreſſed, and hath well diſcuſſed this Argument; <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni animi eſt iniurias deſpicere;</hi> that it was the marke of a poore Spirit, to be touched with Iniuries, and a great Minde, did trample, and contemne them.</p>
            <p>Now the Vertue of Patience, which ſhined in thoſe Heathen Worthies, is not ſufficient, to ſet of that Meekeneſſe, that is required at our hands, or to be a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, for a Chriſtians Imitation. For firſt, that is true, which is Obiected againſt them, by Saint
<hi>Cyprian; Tamillis falſa Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia eſt, quam &amp; falſa Sapientia. They had a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5460:15"/>falſe Patience, becauſe they had a falſe Wiſdome.</hi> The ground of their Patience, was Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and Pride, at the beſt Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: but Chriſtian Meekeneſſe muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, not out of a Vice, or ſhadow of a Vertue, but out of a true ground, or the Mother of all Vertues, that is <hi>Humility,</hi> as I haue already ſhewed. Againe, the Actions of thoſe Heroical Spirits, toward thoſe that did the Iniuries, are onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and we are not aſſured of their Affections, how their Hearts ſtood affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted toward them: but our Heauenly Maſter requireth, as the Complement of our Meekeneſſe, <hi>that we forgiue men their treſpaſſes, Matth.</hi> 6. that is, A free Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all Iniuries: And <hi>Loue your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Matth.</hi> 5. that is, An entire Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on toward their Perſons. Laſtly the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall Patience, went no further then this, <hi>Recompence to no man euill for euill;</hi> and knew nothing of the other degree: But Chriſtian Meekeneſſe muſt exceed this; <hi>But ouercome euill with good.</hi> Like the Meekeneſſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to be blotted out of the Booke of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5460:15"/>Life, for that People, which had murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt God; and whereof ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, had repined, and mutined againſt himſelfe: Or like the Meekeneſſe of our Sauiour Chriſt, which ſo farre ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all compariſon, that euen, as wee all confeſſe,
<hi>Viuificatur Chriſti Sanguine, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am qui fudit ſanguinem Chriſti.</hi> They which crucified our Sauiour Chriſt, are reſtored by the bloud, which their malitious hands haue ſpilled. Now wee haue gone, through the three Vices, oppoſite to this ſecond Kinde of Meekeneſſe. Firſt, Readineſſe, or Proneneſſe to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: Secondly, Harmefulneſſe, or an euill Deſire of Doing wrong: And thirdly, Thirſt of Reuenge, after an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury receiued.</p>
            <p>The Preſeruatiues of Meekeneſſe (for <hi>It cannot be, but that offences will come,</hi> as our Sauiour ſaith) may be diuerſe. The firſt is <hi>Silence;</hi> or <hi>Taciturnity.</hi> And this firſt Precept, is recommended in the 34. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> to him that would lead a quiet life, and deſireth to ſee good daies. <hi>Keepe thy tongue from euill.</hi> As
<hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, in a caſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5460:16"/>not much vnlike, <hi>Cadit ſtatim ſimultas, ab alterâ parte deſerta, niſi par non pugnat.</hi> So where Wrath encountreth with Silence, the Quarrell is lame on the one ſide, and the ſtrife will ſoone be appeaſed. But the contrary hapneth, where it is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held vpon equall termes, as the Comick Poet hath ſaid,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Bacchae baccanti ſi velis aduerſarier</l>
               <l>Ex inſanâ inſaniorem facies.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Beſides, the ſtrife which the Tongue raiſeth, is not worthy the maintaining, if we conſider the Originall of it. It is but a word which pierceth not; <hi>Et tantùm delicatis graue</hi> (as the Moralliſt ſaith) felt onely by them, that are delicate and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and in that impreſſion, rather vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, then hurteth them. And much leſſe, if we conſider the Parties, from whom it vſually comes; <hi>Vt quiſque contemptiſsimus, Et vt miximè ludibriò eſt, ita ſolutiſsimae lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae.</hi> Euer the more lewd, or the more
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooliſh the party be, the more lauiſh of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is tongue he is, and the more liberty we giue him: <hi>And ye ſuffer fooles gladly,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> Another Leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5460:16"/>in the ſame ranke (which is <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Tongue</hi>) is a
<hi>Soft</hi> and <hi>gentle An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. A ſoft anſwer turneth away wrath; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs</hi> 15. And theſe two, may worke one Effect, though by diuers waies: Silence taketh away the Fuell, that the Fire may not burne; but a Soft Anſwer, diſtilleth drops of Water, to put it out. Beſides, a Soft Anſwer, pertaketh ſometimes, of <hi>Iacobs</hi> wreſtling with the Angell, that it obtaineth a Benediction in the end; which was the Effect of <hi>Abigails</hi> Speech to
<hi>Dauid,</hi> that it wrought, not a relenting alone in <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, toward her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Nabal,</hi> but found a more gracious acceptance at his hands; <hi>Bleſſed be thy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and bleſſed be thou, which haſt kept me this day, from ſhedding of bloud.</hi> Another Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue, in the ſame ranke (though it might ſeeme otherwiſe) is a ſharp ſpeech in due ſeaſon. And therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> inſerts this, in his charge to <hi>Timothy, Cum modeſtiâ corripientem: In meekeneſſe reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe that oppoſe themſelues.</hi> So that there is Meekeneſſe in Bitterneſſe, as well as in Sweetneſſe. Such was the Speech
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5460:17"/>of <hi>Abigail</hi> to her Husband <hi>Nabal,</hi> after ſhe had ſaued him, from the wrath of <hi>Dauid.</hi> When <hi>Nabal</hi> was in his wine, it had beene bootleſſe to haue ſpoken, and would haue prouoked him to more fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but after his wine was diſgeſted, ſhe pierced his Soule, that his Heart ſmote within him. Such effect hath a ſharpe reprehenſion, tempered with Modeſty, and Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Preſeruatiue of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is <hi>Ceſsion,</hi> or <hi>giuing place vnto wrath.</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>Auenge not your ſelues, but rather giue place vnto wrath.</hi> What's that, Giue place vnto Wrath, that Wrath ſhould ouerflow in your breaſts? not ſo; but Depart from thine Enemie, whilſt he is in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that ſo thy Abſence, and remouing the Occaſion, might bury thoſe vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py flames, which are kindled betwixt you. This was <hi>Iacobs</hi> Pollicy, to pacifie his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> who being directed by the Counſell of <hi>Rebecca</hi> (and herein ſhe was the Embleme of Patience) depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his Brother, into a far Country,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5460:17"/>and returned not againe, till after many yeeres, when his Brothers wrath was wholly appeaſed.</p>
            <p>The third is, A Motion to Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: which is another Precept, in the fore-recited Pſalme, <hi>Seeke peace, and enſue it.</hi> The Contention is not worthy, who gaue the firſt cauſe of offence, but it is a bleſſed thing, to moue the firſt Stone to Reconciliation. This alſo was after pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, by the Patriarch <hi>Iacob,</hi> who thought it not enough, to giue place vnto wrath, vnleſſe he further endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Reconciliation; and bought it too, with faire language, and large gifts, whereby he ſo mollified his brother <hi>Eſaus</hi> Heart, that in the end, <hi>Praereptae bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionis non meminiſſet, meminiſſet delatae ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactionis,</hi> as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith. The Birthright and Bleſſing were quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; but the Preſents, and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were freſh and powerfull. So now we haue in the generall, three Preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of Meekeneſſe: Gouernement or Brideling of the tongue: Ceſſion or Giuing place vnto wrath; and A Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5460:18"/>or Endeuouring of Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
            <p>There is now one Blot, wherewith this Vertue of Meekeneſſe is ſubiect to be ſtained, from which it will be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, to free and deliuer it. And that is, that howſoeuer it may lurke vnder the name of a Vertue, notwithſtanding it proceedeth from no other Originall, but Defect of Courage, and is in it ſelfe, the Badge of Puſillanimity, and an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect minde. And eſpecially, if it bee ſo, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Ira,</hi> is <hi>Calcar Virtutis,</hi> Anger is the Spurre of Vertue; what then muſt that needs bee, which both dulleth the edge of Vertue, and brings in it ſelfe no warmth, to prouoke forward, vnto any vertuous, or magnanimous Action? But this is not ſo. The Effect of Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is to bee Vanquiſher ouer our owne Paſſions. And the Wiſe man hath ſaid, <hi>Prou.</hi> 16. <hi>He that is ſlow to Anger, is better then the mighty, and he that ruleth his Spirit, then he that taketh a citty.</hi> And the rather, becauſe the Domeſticke Enemy, is more dangerous then the Forraine; and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5460:18"/>commonly thoſe, which haue made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men their thralls, are the greateſt ſlaues, to their owne Paſſions. Beſides, the Spurre, which pricked forward thoſe Heathen Worthies, vnto ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Patience, was not any baſe thought, or Abiectneſſe, but Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and Height of Minde, as hath beene already ſhewed. And who would impute, the Meekeneſſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> vnto any Baſeneſſe, and not rather vnto Height of minde, in ſuffering the foule Reuiler <hi>Shimei,</hi> at ſuch a time, when as <hi>Dauid</hi> was guarded with a Band of Men, all well appointed, and ready at his command, to execute Vengeance, vpon a ſilly vnarmed caitife? Laſtly, the Schoole Diuines, who refer euery one of theſe Beatitudes, to ſome of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt; as <hi>Hunger and Thirſt after Righteouſneſſe,</hi> together with <hi>Mercy,</hi> to the Gift of <hi>Piety; Pouerty in Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Mourning,</hi> to the Gift of the <hi>Feare of the Lord;</hi> doe refer this Vertue of <hi>Meekeneſſe</hi> vnto the Gift of <hi>Might,</hi> or <hi>Fortitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two Vices, which are ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5460:19"/>vnder the name of Meekeneſſe, that ought to be carefully auoided. The one is Senſleſneſſe, or a whole Auerſion, from the Paſſion of Anger; the other Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or Looſeneſſe in our Functions. And theſe two, ought to be thus diuided amongſt themſelues, for the former is a Defect in our Nature, the latter a Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our Manners. We will begin with the former. This Vice is called (where it hath a name)
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and is the other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme, on the Defect of Anger. <hi>Seneca,</hi> who was the ſoareſt Enemy to Anger, would neuer endure, that his <hi>Wiſe man</hi> ſhould be thought deuoid, of the ſenſe of Iniury; For that were, to make him iuſt of the conſtitution of a Stocke, or a Stone, that nothing can penetrate or affect. Beſides this, that it would rob him of the glory, due vnto Patience; <hi>Nulla virtus eſt, quae non ſentias perpeti.</hi> It is no vertue, to ſuffer thoſe things patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of which we are not ſenſible. S.
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> accounts it a greater perfection, to temper the vnrulineſſe of Anger, then to want the inward motions of it; <hi>cùm ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runque
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5460:19"/>hoc lentius, illud fortius aeſtimetur;</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the one is an argument of Ability, and power, the other of Weakeneſſe. Laſtly, the very Exerciſe of Meekeneſſe it ſelfe, preſuppoſeth Anger; for it was deſcribed to be <hi>Moderatiua Irarum,</hi> A Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration about the Paſſion of Anger; And therefore it is to be found, and is moſt excellent in thoſe mindes, which are naturally ſubiect to Anger. And ſure, the Affection of Anger, is in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not onely tollerable, but a Vertue: And therefore, it was truly called by the Academicks, and other Philoſophers, <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fortitudinis,</hi> and <hi>Virtutis Socia:</hi> The Whetſtone of Courage, and the Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate of Vertue; then which two, what more glorious Titles can be giuen, by Heathen Contemplatours? It was the Saying of <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperor, <hi>Alienus ab irâ, alienus à iuſticiâ:</hi> Hee that is free from Anger, will bee free from Doing Iuſtice. He ſpoke it, as an Emperour, vnto whom was required a Mixture of Anger, for the due Execution of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Lawes: and might haue ſpoken it,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5460:20"/>if he had meant it of Vniuerſall Iuſtice, which is the Root, of all the Morall Vertues; Hee that is free from Anger, will be free from all manner of Vertue.
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> makes it a laudable Quality, if it haue due reſtraint, and limitation; of which ſort are, <hi>Quibus de rebus, quibuſque hominibus,</hi> and <hi>Quemadmodùm,</hi> and <hi>Quo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> and <hi>Quamdiù.</hi> For there muſt bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had to the Cauſes, for which; and to the Perſons, towards whom; and to the Manner, how; and to the Seaſon, at what time; and to the Continuance, or laſting of it. <hi>Dauid</hi> in the fourth Pſalme, hath ſet downe an inuiolable Rule for it. Wherein is to be noted in paſſage, that he that could beare the reproaches, of the Vileſt Perſon, could giue the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Precept of Anger. <hi>Be angry, and ſinne not.</hi> There are two things required, to make it a blamleſſe Anger: Firſt, that the cauſe bee warrantable, leaſt it haue the conception of a wicked Anger; Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it be bridled by Reaſon, leaſt it grow into Exceſſe, and degenerate into the Nature of a ſinne. So then <hi>Moſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5460:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>not from his former Meekeneſſe, when hee was ſo farre tranſported for Gods cauſe, that he brake the two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Stone, newly written with the Finger of Gods Hand. <hi>Phineas,</hi> had a good Cauſe, when he ſtood vp to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement, by which he both tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away the Plague, and receiued the Praiſe of Righteouſneſſe, amongſt all Generations. <hi>Elias was a man ſubiect to like Paſsions, as we are,</hi> being once tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with an holy Anger, that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, were generally fallen to ſerue <hi>Baal,</hi> and himſelfe onely left, to ſerue the Lord. Laſtly, the Zeale was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which poſſeſſed our Sauiour, when he ſcourged the Buyers, and Sellers, out of the Temple. Nay whoſoeuer is not Angry, for God, and a good Cauſe, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<hi>Phineas</hi> his Zeale, and <hi>Dauids</hi> vnof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue Anger, and Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Rod, and againe, the Zeale of <hi>Chriſt, The Zeale of thine houſe, hath eaten me vp, Iohn</hi>
2.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is a Remiſneſſe, and Looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in our Functions. This Vice doth often creepe, into the Meeke mans Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5460:21"/>and yet it is, a leſſer Vice, then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme Rigour. For the Meeke Man (as
<hi>S. Gregory</hi> ſaith) doth onely ſuffer a Vice, to ſteale vpon his good Nature, and Vertue; but the teſty, and angry Perſon, doth hotly proſecute a Vice, vnder the name, and pretence of a Vertue. <hi>S. Gregory,</hi> doth grauely obſerue, the difference of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Admonitions, vnto two Perſons, participating of one Affection of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and yet diuided in their temper, and diſpoſition. For <hi>Timothy,</hi> who was more violent and hot, hee ment to take oft from his edge, — <hi>Reproue, rebuke, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, with all long ſuffering, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> But vnto <hi>Titus,</hi> who was of a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der temper, he endeuoureth to adde more Spirit: <hi>Theſe things ſpeake, and exhort, and rebuke, with all Authority</hi> And in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Titus,</hi> is the ſame Admonition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended, vnto euery Meeke Man, in his Function. And this ſhall ſuffice, for the two Vices, ſhrouded vnder the name of Meekeneſſe; the one an Errour in our Nature, the other a Deprauation of our Manners.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:5460:21"/>
            <p>The Second generall part, was the Dignity, or Sublimity of ſuch Perſons, as are eminent in this Vertue of Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> There are foure ſeuerall Kindes, as the Schoole-men obſerue. <hi>Gifts, Vertues, Fruits, Beatitudes.</hi> Gifts, are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, and are almoſt all recited, in the 11. of <hi>Iſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the name of Spirits: <hi>The Spirit of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and vnderſtanding, The Spirit of counſell, and might, the Spirit of knowledge, and of the feare of the Lord.</hi> The Vertues are ſome Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and ſome Theologicall: The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall are,
<hi>Prudence, Temperance, Iuſtice, Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> with other leſſer Vertues; and the Theologicall are <hi>Faith, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe,</hi> and
<hi>Charity.</hi> The Fruits are in part numbred vnto vs, by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the fifth to the <hi>Galatians: But the fruit of the Spirit, is loue, ioy, peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith; Meekeneſſe, temperance.</hi> Laſtly; the Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes are theſe eight, heere in the fifth Chapter of <hi>S Matthew, Pouerty in Spirit, Mourning, Meekeneſſe, Hunger and Thirſt after righteouſneſſe, Mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and ſo forward. Firſt, for Gifts, they are Habits in the Soule,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5460:22"/>which deſcend with the Holy Ghoſt, the God of Loue; and becauſe they can neuer bee diſioyned from Loue, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are peculiarly called by that name, The Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt. The Vertues are likewiſe Habits, whereof ſome are conceiued within the Minde of Man, through the Light of Reaſon, as the Morall Vertues; and ſome are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into the Minde, as the free Gifts of God, namely the Theologicall. The Fruits are like their name, the Iſſues and Fruits of the Spirit within vs, and haue a double reſemblance, vnto corporall Fruits: firſt, that they bee the laſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, of the ſtrength, and vigour of the Spirit; Secondly, that they be delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and pleaſant to the Soule, as fruits are to the taſte. Laſtly, the Beatitudes are outward Actions, and Practiſes; dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from Vertues, as in ſome other reſpects, ſo alſo in this; that Vertues are Habits, and Powers of the Minde; Beatitudes are Practiſes, and Operations of the Vertues. This Eſtate of Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, falls into three of theſe Orders,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5460:22"/>and is both a <hi>Morall Vertue,</hi> one of the <hi>Fruits of the Spirit,</hi> and a <hi>Beatitude.</hi> Firſt, in reſpect of the Morall Part of it, wherewith thoſe noble Spirits, amongſt the Heathen were endued, it is the ſame with <hi>Patience,</hi> a Morall Vertue only, and riſeth no higher. Secondly, as it brings delectation, and content to the Soule, it is one of the <hi>Fruits</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned amongſt them, in that fifth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Galatians.</hi> And in the laſt place, as it is an eminent, and perfect Practiſe of that Vertue, in the life of a Chriſtian, it is one of the <hi>Beatitudes,</hi> and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons excelling in it, are pronounced <hi>Bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Speculations of the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, may ſeeme too curious, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, eſpecially for this Auditory, and therefore are to be touched onely in Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. But I may ſet downe this for Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, that there are three things required in Meekeneſſe, to make it a Beatitude, and to confirme the Profeſſours of it, in the State of Bleſſedneſſe. The firſt is, that it be not an ordinary meaſure of Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5460:23"/>but an Eminency, or Perfection in it. Secondly, that this Meekeneſſe be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God. Thirdly, that it bee in the preſent, an Inchoation, or Beginning of future Bleſſedneſſe. For the firſt. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> aboue the common degree of Vertue, exalteth one kinde which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Heroicall,</hi> which hath that Eminency, that it dignifieth the Profeſſors thereof, with the Title of <hi>Diuini viri,</hi> deriuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them ſome participation of Deity, or Diuinity. This Meekeneſſe, whereof we ſpeake, though it be not an Heroicall Vertue, (for that is too low a degree for a Chriſtian) yet it muſt be ſome ſupere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minent degree, far aboue the poſitiue, qualified not with one Action, or Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, but with many, and conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the attribute of <hi>Beaci viri,</hi> or Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to them that haue it. There wee many things concurring in <hi>Dauids</hi> Meekneſſe, to make it a <hi>Beatitude,</hi> or <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe.</hi> The Perſon of the King, was ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cred, not to he violated, by any lewd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiler: The Rayler was his Subiect, and had his life in the Kings hand: His paſſage
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5460:23"/>at that time warlike, not to be braued, by any bold affront: But the chiefe thing was, his humble Confeſſion of his ſins, <hi>Let him curſe, for the Lord hath bidden him:</hi> And his patient expecting a Recompence at Gods hands, <hi>It may be that the Lord will looke on mine afflictions, and will requite good for his curſing this day.</hi> And ſurely, the Meekeneſſe of Saint <hi>Steuen,</hi> was no leſſe then a Beatitude; imitating the Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt, both in ſuffering Death patiently, and in offring vp his laſt Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for his Perſecutors. And the Effect of his Praiers was ſuch, that hee obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a great Enemy to the Church, and one of the hotteſt in his perſecution, to be afterwards a Valiant Champion for Chriſt. This Meekeneſſe muſt proceed from a double Root;
<hi>Humility,</hi> which is the Exaltation of all Vertues; and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Charity beareth all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Property, required to a Beatitude, is that it muſt bee accepted of God. The Heathen, though they were famous in this, and other Vertues, yet their Meekeneſſe was not accepted of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5460:24"/>God. And as the reaſon is knowne, out of Saint <hi>Paul, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b.</hi> 11. <hi>Without faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God:</hi> So to ſhew, when it comes in a forme, pleaſing vnto him,
<hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> hath ioyned them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her, <hi>He hath pleaſure in faith and Meekeneſſe.</hi> The ſingular Meekeneſſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was of this Kinde; of whom we ſhall read from Gods owne teſtimony; that if a Prophet, had any ordinary Reuelation
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom the Lord, the Lord did appeare vnto him, in a Viſion, or a Dreame; <hi>But my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant Moſes is not ſo,</hi> for he was admitted, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the familiar Conference and Boſome Counſells of the Lord: And the cauſe of this high fauour, and grace which hee had with God, (as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> obſerueth it) was the exceeding meaſure of his Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Dauid</hi> was declared to be <hi>A man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods owne heart,</hi> and it ſeemes, that he was accepted for his Meekeneſſe, when in making Interceſſion to God, he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions this Vertue onely, <hi>Memento Domine Dauid, &amp; omnis manſuetudinis eius: Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Dauid, and all his Meekeneſſe.</hi> So I finde it, in the Latine tranſlation,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5460:24"/>though the Engliſh reads it, <hi>And all his Afflictions.</hi> The third Property, required to a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitude, is that it muſt be in the preſent, an Inchoation, or Beginning of future Bleſſedneſſe. Beatitude is properly, the laſt End of the life of man, vnto which all our Actions are directed, that wee may obtaine it: If it be an apparant Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude onely, it is that of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers; but the true Beatitude, is onely of Chriſtians. Theſe Vertues are called Beatitudes, not becauſe they are the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Rewards, which wee ſhall enioy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life, but becauſe they are Eſtates of life, walking in the Lawes, and fauour of God, and ſo farre aſſured of future Happineſſe, as Hope can poſſeſſe vs of it. And hope is ſo firme, that by it wee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of things future, as if they were now reall and preſent. <hi>By hope we are ſaued,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 ſpeaking in a ſtile, as if we did at the preſent enioy it. Now for Meekneſſe, it is an Eſtate, as firmely poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſing Heauenly Happineſſe, as any of the reſt; <hi>The meeke mans prayers are pleaſing vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5460:25"/>God; Thoſe that bee meeke will hee teach his wayes;</hi> The Meeke Man is apt, and vacant for Heauenly Contemplation; and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>He will beautifie the Meeke with Saluation.</hi> Theſe three things are required, to a Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. Firſt, that it be a Vertue eminent in his kinde. Secondly, that it be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God. Thirdly, that it bee a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of future Happineſſe.</p>
            <p>The laſt generall part of my Text, is the Reward, <hi>For they ſhall inherit the earth.</hi> The Earth, which is implyed in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, may be double. Firſt, this tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Earth, of which it is ſaid, <hi>Heauen and Earth ſhall paſſe away:</hi> on which the Meeke, and the Mighty are mixed both together, and poſſeſſe it without diſtinction. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that immutable, and eternall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, of which it is ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>There ſhall be a new Heauen, and a new Earth;</hi> in which the Meeke ſhall haue the ſole poſſeſſion of the Earth, without diſturbance. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I ſee, but that the promiſe, made by our Sauiour Chriſt, vnto the Meeke, may haue this double reſpect. For it is a certaine Rule, that is obſerued by Saint
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5460:25"/>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi> The promiſes of God, doe not ſo aſſure vs, of our future Happineſſe, that they exclude vs from a temporall Bleſſing: But <hi>ſeeke yee firſt the kingdome of God, and his righteouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall be added vnto you:</hi> neither doe they ſo reach vnto vs, a temporall Bleſſing, but that the Latitude of his promiſe, doth extend to a future. In which ſenſe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writes to
<hi>Timothy; But Godlineſſe is profitable vnto all things, hauing the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> To ſay a little of each. Firſt then it is without Queſtion, that it may bee meant, of this preſent Earth. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, though they had profited in Chriſt, aboue the common Multitude, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they were at this time, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued yet Carnall. Diuerſe Inſtances conuince them thereof afterward, in which they vnderſtood many things, that were ſpoken of Chriſt, carnally: And our Sauiour Chriſt, was well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, how to draw, and allure Carnall Mindes, partly and at the firſt, by tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Promiſes. As for that Pſalme, from
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5460:26"/>whence this text is transferred, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, by the whole phraſe thereof, that it ſtrikes vpon a temporall inheritance. Neither is this without Parallel, in moſt of the Texts, of the old Teſtament, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the Decalogue, or ſumme of the Morall Law, there is but one promiſe, and that of a temporall Bleſſing, granted vnto thoſe, that doe beare due Honour to their Parents. Nor yet without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſeeing that of the great Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which came forth out of Egypt, the Murmurers were all cut off in the paſſage, and the Meeke onely ſuffered to enter, into the Land of Canaan. As for that Interpretation of Saint
<hi>Bernard,</hi> that by the earth are implyed our Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bodies, whereof the Meeke only haue quiet poſſeſſion, in as much as in them, their Affections, and Paſſions are ſubiect vnto Reaſon, it is no idle conceit, and it agreeth alſo with a Temporall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For the ſecond; It is alſo certaine, that the Reward, which is here promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by our Sauiour, doth reach to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Earth; of which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5460:26"/>the 27. <hi>Pſalme, Vnleſſe I had beleeued to ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord, in the land of the liuing.</hi> The Earth here is the Land of the Dying; either of thoſe, which are dead in their ſinnes, or poaſting haſtily to the Coaſts of Death: but the other Earth, whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh, is the Land of the Liuing, and ſhall be the poſſeſſion of thoſe, who are the Inheriters of Life, and Immortality. Beſides this Text is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally a Verſe of the 37. Pſalme, and in that place, (though the greateſt part of the Pſalme bendeth another way) it is not altogether diſioyned, from an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Inheritance;
<hi>But the meeke ſhall inherit the earth, and ſhall delight themſelues, in the abundance of peace.</hi> Abundance of peace, is not the Portion of this World; in which there is neither any ſolid Peace, nor any true meaſured Abundance; but is reſerued to be the Reward of that place;
<hi>In which there is fulneſſe of ioy, and pleaſures for euermore.</hi> Againe,
<hi>Inheritance</hi> is not alone a Lawfull Right, but a Conſtant Poſſeſſion, which is onely the Tenure of the World to come. And laſtly, the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5460:27"/>of the Meeke, is of the ſame Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, with that of the Peace-makers; who are called in the ninth verſe, <hi>the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of God.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the eight to the <hi>Romans, And if Children, then heires, heires of God, and ioynt heires with Chiſt.</hi> And ſo much for the Reward, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Bleſſings of two kindes, which are both temporall, and eternall.</p>
            <p>Let vs now, as good Oratours were wont to doe, recollect the generall Heads, of that which hath beene ſpoken. I haue gone through the three parts of my Text. The firſt was, the Condition, and Eſtate of Men, whom our Sauiour, in this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, pronounceth Bleſſed; <hi>The Meeke.</hi> And in this part, I repreſented vnto you, a rude Modell of Meekeneſſe: wherein I deſcribed firſt the Nature of Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it is <hi>Moderatiua Irarum,</hi> A Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Anger. Next the two Kindes of Meekeneſſe, toward God, and toward Man; and withall the Oppoſite Vices in each kinde: In the firſt kind; Murmuring againſt God, for two Cauſes; for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5460:27"/>Eſtate of the Vngodly, and for the ſuppoſed vnproſperous Eſtate of the Godly. In the other Kinde towards Man, three oppoſite Vices. 1. Readineſſe, or Proneneſſe to Anger. 2. Harmeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or an euill Deſire of Doing wrong. 3. Thirſt of Reuenge, after an Iniury re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. Of this Meekeneſſe toward Man, I obſerued three Preſeruatiues: Gouerning, or Brideling of the Tongue; Ceſſion, or Giuing place vnto Wrath; and a Motion, or Endeuour of Reconciliation. Further leſt this Vertue ſhould haue an euill Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, as the Deſcendant of Baſeneſſe, or Puſillanimity, I haue freed it, from that Ignominy, and Scandall. And laſtly, leſt it ſhould bee obtruded vnder a falſe Vizour, I haue ſeparated two Vices, or Extremes, from it; the one an Errour in our Nature, (Softneſſe, or Dulneſſe of Spirit:) the other in our Manners (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſeneſſe or Looſeneſſe in our Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.) The ſecond generall Part, was the Dignity, or Sublimity of the Meeke:
<hi>Bleſſed.</hi> In which part, I recited foure Kindes: Gifts, Vertues, Fruits, Beatitudes,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5460:28"/>with their differences: Beſide, three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties required to the Conſtitution of a Beatitude. Firſt, that it bee an eminent Vertue, in his owne Kinde. Secondly, that it be accepted of God: Thirdly, that it be an Inchoation of future Bleſſedneſſe. The laſt generall Part, was the Reward, promiſed vnto the Meeke, which inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Bleſſings of two Kindes, that is, both Temporall and Eternall, <hi>For they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Sermon of Meekeneſſe, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue now, ſhould affect moſt of vs, with that Paſſion, which ouertooke the young Man, in the Goſpell, at our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours Counſell of Perfection, that <hi>He went away ſorrowfull.</hi> If wee be Chriſts Diſciples of Meekeneſſe, we ſhall be ſure, to haue our ſhare, of as much Diſcontent, and Vnhappineſſe, as this world can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vpon vs. And who are proper, to be the Footſtoole, of euery arrogant, and ignoble Spirit, but the Meeke? Which portion was long ſince allotted them, by one that had feelingly contemplated of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5460:28"/>that Argument; <hi>They turne the needy, out of the way, the meeke of the earth, hide themſelues together, Iob</hi> 14. But the matter is not thus. For firſt, the Encouragement is not ſmall, which our Sauiour Chriſt annexeth to the end of his Inuitation to Meekeneſſe; <hi>Learne of me, for I am meeke, and lowly of heart, and you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules.</hi> That which all the world cannot giue, will Meekeneſſe aſſure vs. And what is it, to be toſſed, and bruiſed in our Bodies, ſo we enioy that Tranquillity of Minde, and Soule, aboue all the Happineſſe of the world? And next, if we conſider the Perſons, that will trample vpon Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they are none but thoſe harſh, and vngodly Spirits, who, if hee were vpon Earth againe, would not ſpare to afflict, euen the Lord of Meekeneſſe himſelfe, and to crucifie him anew. And for thoſe that are not extremely ill, though Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath not a Weapon to reſiſt, yet it hath Innocency, to protect it ſelfe againſt wrong; and as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cato, Quis enim ſciens Catoni iniuriam faceret?</hi> For who would willingly haue offered any Iniury
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5460:29"/>to <hi>Cato?</hi> But for the Gentle, and Pious Natures, there is nothing that winneth ſo much fauour, and loue from them, as Meekeneſſe doth: And the Counſell of
<hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> is alwaies true; who was expert as well in Morall, as in Diuine Wiſdome: <hi>My ſonne performe thy doings with Meekeneſſe, ſo ſhalt thou be beloued of them that are approued.</hi> But if the caſe of the Meeke man, bee ſo low, as to bee forſaken on Earth, yet he hath an Aduocate, and a Iudge in Heauen, by whom amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other diſconſolate Eſtates, the Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of theſe perſons are not leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, For
<hi>He will argue with Equity for the Meeke of the Earth;</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh Laſlly, becauſe Examples are pregnant to moue vs, eſpecially when we haue ſeene the latter end of them, I will cloſe vp all in one Sentence of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> of extraordinary force, and perſwaſion, <hi>Ye haue heard of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of Iob, and haue ſeene the end of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:5460:29"/>
            <p>The Text, of which I haue ſpoken, is placed in an euen diſtance, betwixt the <hi>Poore</hi> and the <hi>Mercifull.</hi> The obſeruation is not impertinent, for though it bee no member of my Text, yet it is a part of my Errand, to commemorate the thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full praiſes, of theſe poore Children, and other needy Perſons, for your mercifull Affection toward them. I remembred but euen now the Patience of <hi>Iob.</hi> The Aduancement, which that Vertue brought him in the end, is manifeſt out of the Scriptures. There was another thing intermixed with this Mans Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, mentioned by himſelfe, in his 29. chapter, <hi>Benedictio perituri; The bleſsing of him that was ready to periſh came vpon me.</hi> And no doubt but it was a Motiue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which God had reſpect, in the Inſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Happineſſe. This Bleſſing, I reioyce, that I haue ſo good cauſe, to account it your Portion; for whom the Prayers of ſo many Orphans, and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and diſconſolate creatures, are daily ſacrificed: and I deſire of God, that it may not onely be caſt into the Stocke
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5460:30"/>of this City, for your temporall encreaſe, but that it might bee laid vp for you, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that day, when God ſhall diuide his Rewards, for ſuch holy works; <hi>In as much as ye haue done it, to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye haue done it vnto me.</hi> It were a ſhame, if I ſhould not confeſſe, that this Mother City, like another <hi>Dorcas, hath beene full of good workes:</hi> and it is obſerued, that there are erected, in ſome place or other about it, almoſt yearely Monuments of your Bounty. Theſe are laudable works, for the Beauty, and Honour of the place: But yet in a true eſtimation, they can bee held for no better, then the Piles of Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence: It is that worke only towards the Poore, by which you ſhall build you Houſes, vpon a ſure foundation; For <hi>the poore ſhall receiue you into euerlaſting habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Againe, there is no man can deny, but that the Gouernment, and Iuſtice of this City, are indeed famous, and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary: This worke of Iuſtice alone, is like vnto thoſe Sublimed Gifts, whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes; Releefe of the poore comes neareſt to Charity; neither would
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5460:30"/>this prudent Exerciſe of your Iuſtice, giue any better, then a
<hi>tinckling ſound,</hi> without your mixture of Charity. I ſpeake not this to flatter you with praiſes, for that would be like an vnkinde Breath of Wind, to blaſt your toward fruits of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion; but with another intention, that, as the Oratour ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> might bee
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is, that the Praiſes of what you haue done, might be Prouocations and Perſwaſions, vnto freſh Examples of Piety. Laſtly, though I know the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Mercy to bee ſuch, that it loues nothing leſſe then a Trumpet; yet leſt good works ſhould be buried; or looſe this ſpring time of a new Emulation, both in your ſelues, and others, giue me leaue to recite the number of diſtreſſed ſoules, which haue beene releeued by your Bounty, ſince your laſt ſolemne Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vpon this day. &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
